<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Moses and Aaron, the king and the priest by the author of the examination of Tilenus before the triers, in the time of the late rebellion.</title>
            <author>Womock, Laurence, 1612-1685.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 91 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66899</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3346</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20340</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12733995</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12733995</idno>
            <idno type="VID">66527</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66899)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 66527)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 994:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Moses and Aaron, the king and the priest by the author of the examination of Tilenus before the triers, in the time of the late rebellion.</title>
                  <author>Womock, Laurence, 1612-1685.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 74 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A. Maxwell for R. Clavel ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1675.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Laurence Womock. cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:66527:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Moſes and Aaron; THE KING AND THE PRIEST.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By the Author of</hi> the Examination of <hi>Tile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> before the Triers, <hi>in the time of the late Rebellion.</hi>
            </p>
            <bibl>PSAL. 77. the laſt.</bibl>
            <q>Thou leddeſt thy people like a flock by the hand of Moſes and Aaron.</q>
            <bibl>ZECH. 6. 13.</bibl>
            <q>And the counſel of peace ſhall be between them both.</q>
            <p>LONDON: Printed by <hi>A. Maxwell</hi> for <hi>R. Clavel,</hi> at the <hi>Peacock</hi> near the Weſt-end of St. <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1675.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:66527:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:66527:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1 SAM. 24. 5.</bibl>
               <q>And it came to paſs afterward, that Davids heart ſmote him, becauſe he had cut off Sauls Skirt.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THe Service of this day is deſigned to celebrate the glorious <hi>Memory</hi> of King <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Martyr.</hi> Yet he was arraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as a Malefactor, and a <hi>high Court</hi> of Juſtice was erected for his <hi>Trial.</hi> A Court that was no ways <hi>High,</hi> but in <hi>Guilt</hi> and <hi>Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence:</hi> No way capable of the Title of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> but by an <hi>Antiphraſis;</hi> becauſe it was ſo eminently unjuſt, as well in it's illegal Conſtitution, as in their direful proceedings againſt their Royal Soveraign. Yet before this Court he is led, even as a <hi>Lamb to the Slaughter;</hi> and the <hi>Scene</hi> is dreſs'd up, with all the formalities of a legal Trial, that he might with the better Grace
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:66527:3"/> be mocked out of his life, by a <hi>Pageantry</hi> of Juſtice.</p>
            <p>But whether ſuch Barbarous attempts upon the Perſon of a King, by his own <hi>Liege</hi> People, be warrantable in the ſight of Heaven, will be beſt decided by the <hi>vote</hi> and <hi>practice</hi> of a worthy ſubject, who was <hi>a great ſufferer,</hi> under the Power of a <hi>Severe</hi> Soveraign; yet himſelf a <hi>great Prince,</hi> and <hi>a Stout Souldier, and a man after Gods own heart.</hi> Aud upon this Accompt I have made choice of this Text, for the ſubject of my Diſcourſe at this time. <hi>And it came to paſs afterward, that Davids heart ſmote him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had cut off Sauls Skirt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which words do intimate, 1. <hi>Temptation,</hi> and, 2. declare the <hi>Iſſue</hi> of it. The <hi>Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation was,</hi> To deſtroy <hi>Saul,</hi> his Royal Soveraign: 2. The <hi>Iſſue</hi> of it was, an Act of <hi>Policy,</hi> with his <hi>Remorſe</hi> and <hi>Repentnce</hi> for it.</p>
            <p>The firſt words of the Text do refer us to the <hi>Temptation: And it came to paſs af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward.</hi> The latter do report the Iſſue: <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids heart ſmote him, becauſe he had cut off Sauls Skirt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the firſt, we ſhall conſider the ſtrength
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:66527:3"/> of the Temptation; how it was fortified, with what force of argument it was armed, and with what vigour of Importunity it was managed, to aſſault him.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond we ſhall obſerve two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. What <hi>David</hi> did, <hi>He cut off the Skirt of Sauls Military Robe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. What he ſuffered, <hi>His heart ſmote him for it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. The <hi>Temptation</hi> came upon him (as the wiſe-man obſerves Poverty to come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſlothful,) <hi>like an armed man;</hi> and did moſt impetuouſly aſſault him upon ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny accompts. For there was a mighty <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation,</hi> and a ſeeming <hi>neceſſity;</hi> and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious <hi>Providence</hi> and a fair <hi>opportunity,</hi> a cleer <hi>Title</hi> to the Crown and a pretended <hi>Oracle;</hi> to make way and lay claim to it. Theſe were very plauſible arguments, and there wanted not a Combination of Agita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, or a pathetical <hi>Importunity</hi> to inforcethem.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>O peraepretium eſt etiam ipſorum militum audire conſultationem, eo quod exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis verſuta malitia, illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrat juſti men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ſolidam it inconcuſſam.</hi> Chryſoſt. Hom. de D avide et Saule <hi>Eraſ inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prete.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>1. The <hi>Temptation</hi> was armed with a ſpecious kind of neceſſity, which hath no Law to govern it. The implacable malice of <hi>Saul,</hi> and his frequent <hi>Machi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations</hi> to deſtroy <hi>David,</hi> without any cauſe or colour of offence, were a mighty
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:66527:4"/> provocation. His malice being wilful and of this complexion, no duty of <hi>Davids</hi> could poſſibly either oblige or ſatisfie. <hi>Saul</hi> was haunted with an evil Spirit. And when the fit was upon him, none could be found ſo able to apply an effectual remedy as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid:</hi> he is earneſtly invited to attend, the<note place="margin">v. Chap 18. &amp; 19.</note> charmes of his hand and harp do becalm the diſtemper, that did afflict him; yet ſo ignoble, ſo mean, ſo vile was his malice, he paies his Phyſician and muſick with a <hi>Jave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin.</hi> The King of beaſts is not half ſo fierce and raging: The Lion may be made gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and kindneſs will oblige him; where he meets with a due ſubmiſſion, he will exerciſe a Princely Clemency: But ſuch was the perverſe humour of this King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> no duty in <hi>David,</hi> no worthy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance could mitigate his diſpleaſure: <hi>Davids</hi> prudence did increaſe his jealouſy; his merits did inflame his envy, and his beſt Services did the more inrage his malice. When <hi>David</hi> conducted his forces by his own order, his beſt ſucceſs became not only a matter of ſuſpicion, but a crime, as if it had bin an attempt of Treaſon to defeat his enemies. But the moſt unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:66527:4"/> of <hi>Saul's</hi> fears and jealouſies were thoſe, which aroſe upon the account of Gods preſence and bleſſing in his enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizes; he was afraid of <hi>David, becauſe the</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 18 12.</note> 
               <hi>Lord was with him.</hi> But it is the property of a wicked man, to carry the fear of a ſlave towards Almighty God, becauſe he wants that of a dutiful Son, a pious Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant.</p>
            <p>Whether it were out of tenderneſs: or Shame, or Policy; once he was reſolved not to ingage his own hand in ſo Barbarous an Act, as the murthering of him; he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns therefore to take him off by Stratagem, and to ruine him in the way of Generoſity;<note place="margin">1 Sam. 18. 13. with 25.</note> he does advance him to be a Captain: in his Army, but it is with Deſign to have him cut off by the ſword of the Philiſtins; Then he gives him his Daughter in marriage, that<note place="margin">1 Sam. 18. 21. 25.</note> his bed might become a ſnare to him; for his intent was, that <hi>Davids</hi> life ſhould pay for her dowry. When theſe Deſigns and the attempts of <hi>Aſſaſinates</hi> had, through Divine Providence, become improſperous: And when <hi>Davids</hi> incounters with the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtins,</hi> had out of hazard brought him Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, out of peril Triumph; Then <hi>Saul</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:66527:5"/> reſolves to act that part himſelf which was moſt proper for ſo ill a nature, the part of a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and a Butcher. And then he purſues him in his own Perſon, as a Partridg upon the mountains; and many fetters were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed and watchful to intrap him. But Divine Providence was ever ready to ſtep into his reſcue; for one while he is arreſted in his purſuit, by the Spirit of Propheſy, which came upon him; another while he is diverted by the incurſion of the <hi>Philiſtins</hi> into his Territories. And thus the All-wiſe God does order the attempts of malicious enemies to be ſubſervient to his own over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruling Power, for the ſafety of the faithful; but this reſpite from Perſecution was of no long continuance. The <hi>Philiſtins</hi> are no ſooner retired, but like an unwearied Blood-hound <hi>Saul</hi> takes the ſcent afreſh, and follows this <hi>innocent Lamb,</hi> as if he had bin a beaſt of prey; nor can the deſolate wilderneſs ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure him againſt his cauſeleſs Indignation. He does march up ſuch craggy rocks and mountains as threaten the ſubject-vallies with their prominency, and ſtrike terrour into the paſſengers with the danger of their falling; mountains that were almoſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acceſſible,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:66527:5"/> affording no ordinary paſſage, but for wild Goats. His rage was ſo deſperate,<note place="margin">Ad init. cap.</note> his malice ſo deadly, no danger could diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage, no difficulty could ſtop him. He does expoſe himſelf and his whole Army to a perilous expedition, that he might quench his inſatiable thirſt after the innocent blood of a moſt worthy Son and Subject. Now, <hi>Vim vi repellere,</hi> what more frequent? Doth not the very <hi>Law of Nature</hi> warrant the Practice, <hi>To repell force with force?</hi> If <hi>David</hi> had made a virtue of this neceſſity, and ſtretcht out his hand to take away the life of ſuch a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious <hi>Aggreſſor,</hi> in his own defence; ſurely the Argument of <hi>Self-preſervation</hi> was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable in his juſtification; eſpecially, if Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence falls in to ſecond this neceſſity, as it did here; which brings a freſh ſupply to the force of the Temptation.</p>
            <p>2. There was it ſeems, about <hi>Engedi</hi> a vaſt <hi>Cave,</hi> where the Shepherds were wont to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure their Flocks againſt the ſcorching Sun, and ravenous wild beaſts; thither <hi>David</hi> was retired to ſhelter himſelf and that ſmall par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which was his Guard. While the Kings Army was upon their March, Divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which over-rules Nature, and ſteers
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:66527:6"/> the actions of Princes, directs <hi>Saul</hi> into this Cave, whether to take his reſt, or to relieve nature ſome other way is uncertain. Hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>David</hi>'s Officers are animated to tell him, that now he had an opportunity to make that Cave the ſlaughter-houſe and tomb of his deadly Enemy. They tell him that to ſhake hands with ſuch a Providence is to take leave of it; not to embrace it were to ſlight it; not to follow it were to croſs it, and the ready way to provoke God to wink at his deſtruction, who had watched ſo long care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully for his ſafety. What the Prophet ſaid to <hi>Ahab,</hi> in the name of the Lord, after he had diſmiſſed <hi>Benhadad</hi> his deadly enemy, whom the Lord had delivered into his hands: <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King. 20. 42.</note> 
               <hi>thou haſt let go out of thy hands a man whom I appointed to utter deſtruction; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thy life ſhall go for his life, and thy people for his people.</hi> To this effect did thoſe Agita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of <hi>David</hi>'s Army argue, in reſpect of <hi>Saul.</hi> And to inforce the Argument and the Temptation,</p>
            <p>3. They alledg an <hi>Oracle,</hi> which in their opinion had devoted <hi>Saul</hi> to deſtruction, as a <hi>Sacrifice</hi> to Divine Juſtice, and their own <hi>Peace-offering.</hi> For the men of <hi>David</hi> ſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:66527:6"/> him, <hi>Behold the day, of which the Lord ſaid to thee, Behold I will deliver thine enemy into thy hand, that thou mayſt do to him as it ſhall ſeem good unto thee.</hi> Where and when, and by whom this Oracle was delivered is uncertain, whether by <hi>Gad,</hi> or by <hi>Nathan,</hi> or by <hi>Samuel;</hi> but ſuch an Oracle they pretend <hi>David</hi> had received, to ſupport and comfort him in his Perſecutions; and he had made report of it to his followers to encourage them to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here firmly to him. And time and providence being the beſt interpreters of ſuch predictions, they took the confidence upon this occaſion, to plead that it might be put in practice. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe not to act upon ſuch a warrant, would be an inexcuſable remiſneſs, if not a ſtupid cowardice and diſobedience. It would be a means to offend and provoke God, to neglect his own life and ſafety, and to wrong them his moſt faithful ſervants.</p>
            <p>4. That they had adviſed <hi>David</hi> to kill<note place="margin">Verſ. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Saul</hi> is evident, and without doubt they ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the execution with much importunity, as well for their own eaſe, as for their Maſters reſcue. They had been his conſtant Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions in his travels, in his exile, in his du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; many a hard march, many a hungry
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:66527:7"/> meal had they endured under his Conduct, to attend and guard his perſon; many hazards had they run, and many dangers had they eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caped; and now they carried their lives in their hands, while they were hotly purſued by an enraged Prince, and a puiſſant Army. Though <hi>David's</hi> life was the main <hi>quarry</hi> that was hunted after, yet they were part of the <hi>Covie,</hi> and it was the common game to make them prey and booty aſwell as their Maſter. They could not but long to be reſcued out of this jeopardy; To return home and ſit quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly under their own vines, and enjoy their dear Relations: This was a very deſirable ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but not to be hoped for ſo long as <hi>Saul</hi> was ſo implacable. And their ſad experience had convinced them, this malice was ſo mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal it was not to be extinguiſhed but with his life. Nor did they deſire to preſs <hi>David's</hi> ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs or generoſity ſo far as to put the office of an executioner upon him: They deſired but his <hi>Order,</hi> nay his <hi>leave</hi> had been ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent warrant to them to attempt his reſcue with their own. And being thus redeemed out of his enemies hand, and out of his Juriſdiction too, this would have been a <hi>Crowning Mercy</hi> unto <hi>David,</hi> and have put it abſolutely into
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:66527:7"/> his power to reward their honeſt and ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Loyalty. Therefore if not out of love to himſelf, yet out of kindneſs and a grateful compliance with them, he was obliged to li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten to their counſel. For though careleſs of his own ſafety, yet to betray theirs was inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity; if his own life were not dear to him, yet (when he has the remedy in his own hands, and may ſo eaſily prevent it) to let them ſtill dwell in danger, was ſuch a piece of impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence as was not pardonable in a Soldier and a General; being inhanſed by a double guilt 1. of unkindneſs, and 9. ingratitude. And theſe united Grievances might amount to ſo high a provocation, as to beget a <hi>mutiny</hi> in his party, and induce them to conſult their own peace, and leave him to ſhift for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
            <p>5. And no doubt they did inforce the temptation further upon the account of his ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to the Crown; and ſo twiſted his inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt into the argument together with their own. <hi>David</hi> was the Lords <hi>Anointed,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared <hi>Heir-Apparent</hi> to the Kingdom by a ſentence from Heaven. God (ſay they) has <hi>intail'd</hi> the Crown upon thee, and wilt thou be ſo tame as to ſuffer Gods declared enemy
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:66527:8"/> to cut off that intail, by taking away thy life, before thou canſt inherit? <hi>Saul</hi> knows very well upon whom the Crown is to deſcend; ſo<note place="margin">Verſ. 20.</note> that in ſeeking to deſtroy thee he fights a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, and attempts to croſs the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of Heaven, and to fruſtrate the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of the moſt High. To fight againſt him therefore is to fight the Lords battel; to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move him is the way to accompliſh Gods re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed will together with his ſecret Benepla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citure, and to eſtabliſh thy ſelf according to Gods Ordinance. <hi>Saul</hi> hath rendred himſelf unworthy of the Crown, and unfit to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern; he hath ruin'd himſelf and the whole Kingdom; barbarouſly ſlain the Prieſts and Servants of the Lord, and ſpared thoſe ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies whom the Lord had expreſly devoted to deſtruction. We have the Prophets declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>That the Lord is departed from him; That</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 15. 12. 13. 27.</note> 
               <hi>he hath rejected him, and rent away his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and given it unto thy ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When he is diveſted of his Princely Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and Regal Majeſty, and the Crown ſetled upon thy head by an Act of Heaven; not to aſſert thine own right and title is more than an effeminate weakneſs, it can be no leſs than a ſupine ſtupidity. And has the holy Oyl been
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:66527:8"/> poured upon thy head to ſo little purpoſe? If that Oyl has made thy perſon ſacred, has it added no vigour, no activity to thy ſpirit? He that has given thee the Crown hath given thee the ſword alſo to ſecure and guard it; and not to draw it in thy own defence is to receive it in vain. Give ſome proof of thy Princely Proweſs and Magnanimity, and ſuffer not thy Title to be any longer ſubject to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute or queſtion. Lay hold upon the preſent opportunity, which a happy Providence hath put into thy hand; and let this day be the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod of his reign, that it may be the commence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thy own. Theſe we may imagine were the Arguments which <hi>Davids</hi> Servants had muſtered up to ſtrengthen their tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when they did advance the propoſition to aſſault his Loyalty.</p>
            <p>And now behold the <hi>Philoſophical</hi> modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of <hi>Davids</hi> ſpirit. Behold a <hi>Conflict,</hi> a <hi>Victory,</hi> a <hi>Crown</hi> and <hi>Triumph.</hi> That Cave was the field, and the Combate was wonderful; <hi>David</hi> wreſtles, and Anger played the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion. <hi>Saul</hi> was the matter of the Combate, God the ſpectator and the judg. What a ſharp Conflict was here betwixt Senſe and Reaſon, Self-love &amp; Loialty, kindneſs towards his ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:66527:9"/> friends, and allegiance towards his dread Soveraign? But <hi>David</hi> was as firm and ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt as a Rock in his reſolved integrity. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the memory of former ſufferings, nor the ſenſe of preſent ſtreights, nor the fear of fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture dangers, nor the ſolitude of King <hi>Saul,</hi> nor the imporunity of his own party, nor the hopes of impunity, nor the poſſeſſion of the Kingdom upon the death of <hi>Saul,</hi> could pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with him to avenge himſelf, or ſhake his ſtedfaſt Loyalty.</p>
            <p>This victory was more glorious than his tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph over the Giant, the proud <hi>Philiſtine;</hi> for there he ſubdued but a ſingle enemy, but here he conquered himſelf and his whole Army. <hi>Saul</hi>'s life was precious in <hi>David</hi>'s<note place="margin">1 Sam. 16. 21.</note> eyes, and he did abhor to kill him. Nor was this <hi>Policy</hi> in <hi>David,</hi> but <hi>Conſcience.</hi> That which was <hi>Saul</hi>'s fear, was his beſt ſecurity. He was afraid of <hi>David, becauſe God was with</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 18. 12.</note> 
               <hi>him.</hi> And why ſo? <hi>God doth reſtrain the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Princes: And he it was that bridled up the ſpirit of David.</hi> As <hi>Joſeph</hi> in another caſe, <hi>How ſhall I do this great wickedneſs and ſin againſt God?</hi> Such a wickedneſs <hi>David</hi> deemed it to take away <hi>Saul</hi>'s life; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when he had him at another time at the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:66527:9"/> like advantage, he gave this charge to his Captain <hi>Abiſhai, Deſtroy him not, for who</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 26. 9.</note> 
               <hi>can ſtretch forth his hand againſt the Lords Anointed, and be guiltleſs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But this Prince was wilful, mercileſs,<note place="margin">Agitator.</note> and a <hi>Tyrant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol.</hi> We are obliged to be dutiful, <hi>Not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 17, 18.</note> 
               <hi>to the juſt and gentle, but alſo to the moroſe and froward.</hi> And if I be under a violent perſecution, it is not lawful for me, <hi>vim vi repellere,</hi> to incounter force with force; but when the Aggreſſor is my equal or fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubject: And then it muſt be done, <hi>cum inculpata tutela,</hi> when I can make no eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape by flight, and have no other way for my defence. But my Prince has his Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity over me from Heaven; and therefore I muſt be ſubject to him, out of <hi>Conſcience, as for the Lords ſake.</hi> The ſword is put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his hand by Almighty God; and for<note place="margin">For the King is not anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed over ſingle Perſons, but over Gods In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, 1 Sam. 10. 1. &amp; Chap 15. 17. the head of the Tribes.</note> any private Perſon, or any <hi>Club</hi> of ſubjects, * to wreſt it out, is a double Uſurpation. They do invade Gods <hi>Sovereignty,</hi> who ſay, <hi>Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance is mine</hi> and the Princes <hi>Perogative,</hi> whoſe office it is to <hi>protect</hi> and <hi>puniſh;</hi> when
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:66527:10"/> we will be our own Protectors, and defend our ſelves againſt the order of God and Man, we deſervedly forfeit the Protection of them both.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But that Power, which God had put into this Prince's hands to inable him to Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect, he did imploy to perſecute.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol.</hi> Why in that caſe, there is no neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity to reſiſt, becauſe then, God has made it our duty to ſuffer. <hi>And it is better, if</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3. 17.</note> 
               <hi>the will of God be ſo, to ſuffer for well-do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing than for evil-doing.</hi> God gives thee an opportunity to exerciſe thy Faith and Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; thy ſelf-denyal and thy meekneſs; thy Equanimity and generous Reliance upon him. And when he calls thee to this ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, he is well able to reward thee for it. <hi>Bleſſed are they that are perſecuted for righteouſneſs ſake.</hi> You are not left without a precedent; <hi>For the joy that was ſet before</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 10. 1 Pet. 3. 14.</note> 
               <hi>him,</hi> Chriſt himſelf was pleaſed, <hi>to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the Croſs and deſpiſe the ſhame.</hi> And he<note place="margin">Heb. 12. v. 2.</note> left us an example that we ſhould <hi>not avenge our ſelves, but follow his ſteps in</hi> Obedience un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to blood, <hi>committing both our cauſe and our ſelves</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 21, 23.</note> to him, <hi>who judgeth righteouſly.</hi> And this was
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:66527:10"/> exactly <hi>Davids</hi> Practice. <hi>The Lord judg be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 24. 12, 13.</note> 
               <hi>me and thee, and the Lord avenge me of thee; but mine hand ſhall not be upon thee. As ſaith the Proverbs of the Antients,</hi> Ab impiis egredietur impietas, (<hi>which is,</hi>
               <note place="margin">H. <hi>Card.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>an argument,</hi> quod impium eſt ſe ulciſci) <hi>wickedneſs proceedeth from the wicked, but mine hand ſhall not be upon thee.</hi> This was his profeſſion unto <hi>Saul;</hi> and his complaint to Almighty God was to the ſame effect; <hi>Princes have perſecuted me without a cauſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. v. 161.</note> 
               <hi>but my heart ſtands in aw of thy word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But the Souldiers do here remind<note place="margin">Agitators.</note> 
               <hi>David</hi> of ſomething that had bin delivered by God himſelf in favour of their preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol.</hi> When Souldiers turn Preachers, every Act of Providence that ſeems to favour their deſigns, ſhall be the voice of God; every opportunity to do miſchief to ſuch as they oppoſe, ſhall be interpreted a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand from Heaven to do it. And for ought appears in the ſacred Text, there was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe in their Allegation. Let us grant that the Lord had ſaid to <hi>David</hi> in expreſs Terms; <hi>Behold, I will deliver thine enemy into thy hand:</hi> Yet he did not determin the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:66527:11"/> Perſon; he did not tell him, That enemy was his <hi>Sovereign:</hi> If he had ſaid expreſly; <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, I will deliver</hi> Saul <hi>into thy hand;</hi> Yet, what to do, had bin a further queſtion? what? to kill him; no, <hi>that thou maiſt do</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſ. 4.</note> 
               <hi>to him, as it ſhall ſeem good to thee.</hi> And a loyal heart will Interpret this of an hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py opportunity to ſhew a ſignal duty and kindneſs; not take it for a commiſſion to deſtroy him, againſt ſo many Pregnant In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdictions to the contrary. And this was the ſence and the ſentence of <hi>David,</hi> and he was a Prophet.</p>
            <p>3. For the argument drawn from <hi>Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> it is not only irrational and unſafe but impious. When <hi>Judas</hi> committed a rape upon Divine Providence to gratifie his Avarice, he did highly aggravate his own guilt: ſo our Bleſſed Saviour argues the caſe before <hi>Pilate, Thou couldſt have no Power</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 19. 11.</note> 
               <hi>at all againſt me, except it were given thee from above; therefore he that delivered me unto thee hath the greater ſin.</hi> And ſure <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> had not taken Divine Providence by the right handle, if he had abuſed it unto <hi>Parricide;</hi> As long as he continued ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt in his duty, he might rely upon it, that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:66527:11"/> Providence was not weary to protect him, but awake to watchover him, and to put him into poſſeſſion of the Throne, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it ſhould legally become void for him. But we cannot offer a greater contumely to Almighty God, than to ſet his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence at variance with his Commands, and make his Goodneſs contradict the Juſtice of his own Ordinance. If it be lawful to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the plain path of his Commands, to follow the maze of Providence; then the misfortunes of any Adverſary would be a good warrant to deſtroy him, and the rule of our practice ſhould not be, as the Apoſtle hath ſet it, <hi>If thy enemy hunger, feed him; if he thirſt, give him drink:</hi> but thus, <hi>If thy enemy hunger,</hi> ſtarve him; <hi>if he thirſt,</hi> give him gall and vinegar, and <hi>heap coales of fire upon his head:</hi> Not to <hi>melt</hi> him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a reconciliation and kindneſs, but to <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume</hi> him into aſhes. And if this had bin warrantable, what had <hi>Davids</hi> own doom bin, when he was forced to flee from the face of <hi>Abſalom?</hi> when God had <hi>put out his Glory, and caſt his Throne down to the ground?</hi> Then the Inference had bin Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fragable, <hi>Perſecute him and take him, for there
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:66527:12"/> is none to deliver him.</hi> But this is ill <hi>Logick</hi> and worſe <hi>Divinity.</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>—Careat ſucceſſibus opto,</l>
               <l>Quiſquis ab eventu facta notanda putet.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Let us reflect upon <hi>Davids</hi> imprecation againſt ſuch as follow Providence, that they may add affliction to affliction. <hi>Let their Table be made a ſnare, and their wellfare a trap, pour out thine indignation upon them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 69. 26.</note> 
               <hi>and let their habitation be deſolate; why? for they perſecute him whom thou haſt ſmitten; and they talk to the grief of thoſe whom thou haſt wounded.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4. 'Tis true <hi>David</hi> was anointed to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, but till he was duly put into poſſeſſion, he was but a <hi>Subject:</hi> And being <hi>heir</hi> Apparent to the Kingdom, it became him ſo much the leſs to be a <hi>Traitor</hi> to that Crown, to which he had ſo fair a <hi>Title.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>5. And to be afflicted in the <hi>Minority</hi> of his exaltation, may be of Singular advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to him. The <hi>Rod</hi> may diſcipline the <hi>Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and he that has felt how <hi>keen</hi> the ſword is, may learn by that ſad experience, to manage it ſo much the better; when it is actually put into his hands by the Lord of <hi>Hoſts;</hi> he that has practiſed obedience in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:66527:12"/> the <hi>Paſſive</hi> ſence, knows the better how to govern others. <hi>The Captain of our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation was made perfect through ſufferings.</hi> And herein <hi>David</hi> was to be his <hi>Type;</hi> and therefore he muſt not aſcend the throne upon ſteps made by the treaſonable ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his Predeceſſor, but be led to it by the <hi>Croſs,</hi> and take Perſecution in the way to his <hi>Coronation.</hi> And his faithful Servants muſt be content to <hi>ſuffer with him,</hi> that they may be advanced and <hi>glorified together.</hi> And thus much of the Agitators plea, and of that Combination of Probabilities which did concur to attempt his loyalty, <hi>viz. Provocation</hi> and a ſeeming <hi>Neceſſity, Prediction</hi> and <hi>Providence, Opportunity</hi> and a juſt <hi>Title</hi> to the Crown, with the <hi>Importunity</hi> of almoſt forlorn Adherents.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> We have the <hi>Iſſue</hi> of the Temptation in two particulars:</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. In what David did.</item>
               <item>2. In what he ſuffered.</item>
            </list>
            <p>1. He did not ſlay <hi>him;</hi> he abhorr'd that practice, <hi>Sauls</hi> life was precious in his eyes. But to prevent a further miſchief of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged Souldiers, he aroſe up himſelf, <hi>and cut
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:66527:13"/> off the Skirt of his military robe.</hi> And he had a threefold end in it.</p>
            <p>1. To confute the <hi>Calumnies</hi> of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, who had accuſed him for a <hi>Traytor;</hi> wherefore, ſaith he, doeſt thou give ear to the inſinuations <hi>of thoſe men,</hi> who would perſwade thee, <hi>that David ſeeks thy life?</hi> [Where by the way we may obſerve, that <hi>David</hi> does not impute it to <hi>Saul's</hi> incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, (his duty taught him to believe the King of himſelf would do no wrong;) but to the malice of ſome Sycophants. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, thine eyes ſee, that the Lord hath this day delivered thee into my hands, and I was adviſed to kill thee; but mine eye hath ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red thee, for I ſaid, I will not put forth my hand againſt my Lord, for he is the Lords Anointed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. And hereby he does vindicate his own <hi>Innocency.</hi> As it was a demonſtration of Chriſt's Power to make a reſcue, when the Souldiers which came to apprehend him, were ſtruck down backward at the dread of his preſence: So it was a Demonſtration of <hi>Davids</hi> Innocencie, that he <hi>cut off but Sauls skirt,</hi> when it was in his Power to cut off his life. <hi>My Father, ſee the skirt of thy Robe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:66527:13"/> in my hand.</hi> My taking this only, and not thy life from thee, is a clear evidence, That I have no Treaſon or Malice in my heart againſt thee. And <hi>David</hi> had</p>
            <p>A Third end in it: To <hi>convince Saul</hi> of the error into which ſome <hi>Sycophants</hi> had miſled him, and to melt him into reconcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation and kindneſs: And ſo it happened; for <hi>Saul</hi> melted into tears, and an ingenuous acknowledgment of <hi>Davids</hi> tender loyalty: <hi>And it came to paſs when David had made an end of ſpeaking theſe words unto Saul, that Saul ſaid, Is this thy voice, my ſon David? And Saul lift up his voice, and wept; and he ſaid to David, Thou art more righteous then I; for thou haſt rewarded me good, whereas I have rewarded thee evil. And thou haſt</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 16. to 20.</note> 
               <hi>ſhewed this day how thou haſt dealt well with me, for as much as when the Lord had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered me into thy hand, thou killedſt me not; for if a man find his enemy, will he let him go well away? Wherefore the Lord reward thee good for that thou haſt done unto me this day.</hi> This was the firſt, What <hi>David</hi> did.</p>
            <p>2. What he <hi>ſuffered;</hi> His heart <hi>ſmote him.</hi> There was a <hi>palpitation</hi> of the heart doubtleſs in him, through the commotion
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:66527:14"/> of his blood and ſpirits, and the tumult of his paſſions. For hope and fear, anger and compaſſion, were in conflict, while he was upon ſuch a hazardous attempt. But this in the Text was not a <hi>natural palpitation</hi> of the heart, but a <hi>check,</hi> nay <hi>a ſharp ſtroak</hi> of Conſcience. For ſhew me <hi>a guilty</hi> Perſon, and I will preſently ſhew thee his <hi>lictor,</hi> his Tormentor: Shew me a <hi>Traitor,</hi> and I will ſhew thee a <hi>Scaffold</hi> where the <hi>block</hi> and <hi>Axe</hi> lyes for his <hi>Execution;</hi> that is, the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> of the <hi>malefactor:</hi> Conſcience is the <hi>Centinel</hi> of the Soul, placed there to deſcry the enemy upon his approach, to give us the <hi>Alarm</hi> and notice of the danger; If the enemy hath ſtoln upon us, and entred our Quarters by ſurprize, it is his office then to check us, and rouſe us up to make reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and expel him. And upon this account, and to this effect did <hi>Davids</hi> heart ſmite him. For <hi>David</hi> found himſelf guilty, and the <hi>Rabins</hi> ſay, he was afterwards pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhed by <hi>Retaliation,</hi> when his own gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments would not ſerve to keep him warm. Yet others tell us he was <hi>Innocent,</hi> for what he did was to a <hi>good end,</hi> and out of an <hi>honeſt and good intent;</hi> only, ſay they, it
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:66527:14"/> is the part of good minds to ſtartle at the <hi>Face</hi> of the <hi>Serpent,</hi> at the appearance of evil, and to fear guilt where really there is none to be found. But, by the favour of theſe <hi>Civil Advocates,</hi> a <hi>good end</hi> cannot ſanctifie a <hi>bad action:</hi> If the fact be <hi>unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent,</hi> a good <hi>meaning</hi> can never give it a good Complexion. We muſt not make our Prince his weakneſs a <hi>Foile</hi> to ſet off our own integrity. When <hi>Hanun</hi> had cut<note place="margin">1 Sam. 10.</note> off the garments of his Ambaſſadors, <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> could not but reſent the affront, and was ſo highly incenſed at it, he revenged it with a ſharp Hoſtility. And ſhall <hi>David</hi> offer ſuch an indignity to the King his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter? Kings are jealous of their Honours; and good ſubjects are modeſt upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, fearful many times to receive due praiſe, leſt it ſhould beget ſuſpition, and raiſe envy, by a miſconſtruction, as if it were a means to draw the eyes and hearts of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects from their Prince to themſelves: for this reaſon <hi>Joab</hi> when he had beſieged <hi>Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bah</hi> and brought it to ſo great diſtreſs, it could not hold out a ſtorm; he ſends to his Prince to come and take the honour of the Conqueſt: <hi>Now therefore gather the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:66527:15"/> reſt of the People together, and encamp againſt</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 12. 28.</note> 
               <hi>the City and take it, leſt I take the City, and it be called after my name.</hi> It ſounded ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry harſh in <hi>Saul</hi>'s ears, he did not like the muſick at all, when the women ſung to their Tabrets, <hi>Saul hath ſlain his thouſands,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 18. 6.</note> 
               <hi>and David his ten thouſands.</hi> For a ſubject to be eminently proſperous againſt his Princes enemies, is not always ſafe for him; but to attempt any thing againſt his Perſon that may leſſen his <hi>Grandeur</hi> or his <hi>Prudence</hi> in the eſteem or opinion of his People, is <hi>inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious;</hi> and if it be a matter of reproach to his <hi>Royal Dignity,</hi> it is more <hi>heinous,</hi> and amounts to <hi>Treaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doſt thou ſee thy Prince <hi>cover his feet</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> (as it is ſaid here of <hi>Saul</hi>)? Doſt thou ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve any thing <hi>undecent</hi> in his converſation? Thou mayeſt have a loyal heart, no deſign to deſtroy him; but draw not out the ſword of a <hi>virulent</hi> tongue, <hi>to cut off his skirt</hi> (to diminiſh his due eſteem and ſplendour), to <hi>curtail</hi> his <hi>Robe</hi> of <hi>Defence</hi> and <hi>Dignity;</hi> the <hi>wealth,</hi> and <hi>ſtrength,</hi> and <hi>honour,</hi> and <hi>reputation</hi> of a Prince; for his <hi>Prudence, Juſtice, Valour;</hi> and other <hi>Virtues,</hi> are as his <hi>Military Robe;</hi> They do clothe, defend,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:66527:15"/> and adorn his <hi>Majeſty.</hi> If any paſſion or temptation hath prevailed with thee to cut off any <hi>Skirt</hi> of this Robe, to eclipſe or impair any of thy Princes <hi>Intereſt;</hi> Recollect thy ſelf, and reflect upon the offence, and let thy heart <hi>ſmite thee;</hi> and as a fruit of thy true repentance, ſtudy to make amends for it. So did <hi>David, confregit viros ſuos;</hi> His Party were bent to murder <hi>Saul,</hi> but he broke their obſtinate reſolution, by his loyal exhortation, <hi>The Lord forbid,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that I ſhould ſtretch forth my hand againſt Saul;</hi> For though there be nothing in his <hi>nature,</hi> nothing in his <hi>temper,</hi> nothing in his <hi>carriage</hi> toward us, that may oblige me; yet there is a <hi>civil obligation</hi> lyes upon me,<note place="margin">Ver. 6, 7.</note> he is my <hi>Maſter;</hi> and a pious Reverence I owe him, for <hi>he is the Lords anointed.</hi> When he could alledg nothing elſe, he doth fetch an argument from heaven to plead on his behalf; though <hi>non propter ſanctita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem,</hi> yet, <hi>propter ſacramentum:</hi> God hath put the <hi>holy oile</hi> upon him, and that renders his Perſon <hi>Sacred</hi> and inviolable. The <hi>Grace</hi> that has <hi>dignified</hi> him, doth reſtrain me; whatever the qualities of his natural Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution are, His <hi>Majeſty</hi> is <hi>moſt excellent;</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:66527:16"/> and as he is Gods <hi>Vicegerent,</hi> I muſt have a <hi>Religious veneration</hi> for him. And wtih theſe arguments he breaks the ſtubbornneſs of his rough Soldiers, and charms them into calmneſs and ſubmiſſion.</p>
            <p>And now tell me, Shall we take our <hi>Creed</hi> in this point of <hi>Loyalty,</hi> from the <hi>Sword-man,</hi> or from the <hi>Prophet?</hi> Shall we govern our Practice by the bloody Counſel of the <hi>Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers</hi> of <hi>Fortune,</hi> or by the Judgment and Practice of the <hi>man after Gods own heart?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What a vaſt diſtance, what a direct op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition there is betwixt the Principles of <hi>David,</hi> and thoſe of our late pretended <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Party,</hi> the bloody <hi>Tragedy</hi> that was act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this Day upon our Gracious King of ever bleſſed memory, doth ſufficiently witneſs.</p>
            <p>If Divine Providence allow'd them an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity for this their attempt of Parracide, it was deſigned for their trial, and as well to ſhame, as to diſcover their ſecret malice and hypocriſie. They had no <hi>Provocation</hi> but their own <hi>Guilt;</hi> no <hi>neceſſity</hi> but of their own making; no <hi>Prediction</hi> but a mercenary <hi>Almanack;</hi> and I am ſure, no <hi>Title</hi> to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, but what was pleaded by the <hi>Huſband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> in the Goſpel, <hi>This is the heir, come let
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:66527:16"/> us kill him, and ſeize upon his Inheritance.</hi> And this Argument, preſſed by their own Ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice and Ambition, with the <hi>Clamours</hi> of a malicious giddy multitude, prevailed.</p>
            <p>What <hi>Jacob</hi> upon his death-bed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queathed to thoſe Brethren in iniquity, I ſhall apply to them, and ſo conclude; <hi>Simeon and Levi</hi> (for they went by couples, whether you count them by <hi>Nation,</hi> or by Faction, mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters not) <hi>are brethren, Inſtruments of cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty are in their habitation. O my ſoul, come not thou into their ſecrets; unto their Aſſembly, my honour, be not thou united: For in their anger they ſlew a man;</hi> A man of <hi>Gods right hand;</hi> A man (as much as any) <hi>after Gods own heart;</hi> the beſt of men, and the beſt of Princes: <hi>And in their ſelf-will they digged down a wall;</hi> A Government that was a Bulwark to our lives, our liberties, our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes; to defend them from violence and invaſion: <hi>Curſed be their anger for it was fierce, and their wrath for it was cruel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But God be bleſſed, who hath repaired that Wall, by reſtoring the Son of that <hi>Royal Martyr</hi> to reign over us.</p>
            <p>And for ſuch of that <hi>Combination</hi> and <hi>Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therhood,</hi> whoſe hearts are ſtill ſo reconciled
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:66527:17"/> to their bloody Practices, that they do not yet <hi>ſmite them; Jacobs</hi> Propheſie (which follows in the very next words) be their portion; <hi>I will divide them in Jacob, and ſcatter them in Iſrael;</hi> Let their <hi>Factions</hi> be <hi>as the duſt before the wind;</hi> and their deſigns as <hi>the graſs upon the houſe-top,</hi> that <hi>withereth before it be pluck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let thy hand, O Lord, be upon the man of thy right-hand, our <hi>Gracious Sovereign; make him ſtrong for thine own ſelf; Clothe his enemies with ſhame, upon himſelf let his Crown flouriſh:</hi> That under his Government we may lead <hi>a quiet and peaceable life in all godlineſs and honeſty.</hi> So we thy People, and the ſheep of thy Paſture, will give thee thanks for ever, and ſhew forth thy Praiſe to all generations.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:66527:17"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>NUMB. 17. 10.</bibl>
               <q>And the Lord ſaid unto Moſes, Bring Aarons rod again before the Teſtimony, to be kept for a token againſt the Rebels; and thou ſhalt quite take away their murmurings, from me, that they die not.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>WHen the flames of diſſention do break out in the houſe of God, a Religious Prince can do nothing more noble, nothing more becoming his Royal Office, than to bring water to quench it. God having in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted him with the Supream Power, is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed alſo to depoſite the Court-rolls of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven<note place="margin">Deut. 17. 18.</note> in his hands. He creates him, <hi>Cuſtos utri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Tabulae, Defender of the Faith,</hi> and a <hi>Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Father</hi> of the Church. <hi>David</hi> even for Gods ſake was glad to be <hi>a door-keeper in the houſe of God,</hi> that he might ſhut out profana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and debar intruders from invading the Sacred Office, and committing a Rape upon
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:66527:18"/> Holy Things. Beſides, there is no Prince ſo ſtrong in his <hi>Militia,</hi> and the <hi>affections</hi> of his people, but he will ſtand in need of Gods aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance; and the Prieſts intereſt lies chiefly here. Though weak and defenceleſs in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, yet he hath the conduct of a Spiritual <hi>Militia; Preces &amp; Lacrymae,</hi> Prayers and Tears are at his Devotion. And theſe can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with God, and bring relief, if diſtreſſed, unto <hi>Caeſars</hi> Legions. So that <hi>Intereſt</hi> alone is ſufficient to procure a reciprocal aid between them. The Prieſt is obliged to pay Homage to the Prince, to bleſs him in Gods name, to honour him before the people; and the Prince is reciprocally obliged to ſuccour and ſupport the Prieſt. <hi>Aaron</hi> was aſſigned to <hi>Moſes</hi> for a <hi>coadjuton,</hi> to be his Prophet, his Spokeſman<note place="margin">Exod. 7. 1.</note> to God and to the people. And <hi>Moſes</hi> was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned to be to <hi>Aaron</hi> inſtead of God, a <hi>Sun,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 4. 16.</note> and a <hi>Shield,</hi> a <hi>Defence and Comfort.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed Controverſies in Religion are ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom managed with that temper, that ſhould keep them within their proper ſphere. Men for the moſt part contending not ſo much for Truth as Victory: Debates commonly beget Animoſities, and thoſe Animoſities are fomen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into Parties and Factions. So that a <hi>Schiſm</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:66527:18"/> can no ſooner ariſe in the Church, but it is preſently attended with <hi>Sedition</hi> in the State. When the Church is in jeopardy through the commotions of a tumultuating people, the fluctuation of thoſe raging waters does uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally make the State ſick, put the whole body Politick into a diſtemper. If <hi>Aaron</hi> be diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed in his Office, <hi>Moſes</hi> cannot long ſit quiet upon his Throne. Divine Providence doth thus order it, that the Prince may find him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf concern'd, as well in kindneſs to himſelf, (for his own tranquillity) as in love to God, to becalm ſuch raging tempeſts, to bridle and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain ſuch ſtubborn diſpoſitions. When the offices of Prince and Prieſt were united in one ſingle perſon (as they were in <hi>Melchizedec,</hi> and by the law of nature in the firſt-born;) the neceſſity hereof was more viſible, but not more important. When the adminiſtration of theſe Offices is committed to diſtinct perſons, their intereſt is ſo mixt and twiſted, that like Twins they thrive and fade, live and die toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Though the pretended quarrel be for <hi>Liberty</hi> in Matters of Religion, yet the Inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection hereupon is as well <hi>againſt Moſes as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Aaron.</hi> Hereupon the <hi>Crown</hi> and the <hi>Myter,</hi> the <hi>Scepter</hi> and the <hi>Croſier</hi> are concern'd
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:66527:19"/> in Prudence to ingage in an inviolable league, for the mutual defence of one another. Upon this account <hi>Moſes</hi> doth eſpouſe the quarrel of the Prieſthood, owns its Intereſt, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes its <hi>Patron</hi> under all perils. And this he does not fondly and raſhly, but in the fear of God, and upon good advice; yea by Gods own order and appointment. <hi>And the Lord ſpake unto Moſes,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Here we have a great controverſie about a <hi>Title of office.</hi> The office of the <hi>Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood;</hi> In which there are three things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable:</p>
            <p>1. The <hi>Caſe,</hi> 2. The <hi>Trial,</hi> 3. The <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Caſe</hi> is <hi>Aaron's;</hi> wherein we ſhall conſider, 1. The <hi>Competitors,</hi> (amongſt whom we ſhall find a <hi>Plaintiff</hi> and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant). And 2. <hi>The Patron.</hi> In the 2. the <hi>Trial;</hi> we ſhall conſider, 1. the <hi>Jury,</hi> and 2. the <hi>Verdict.</hi> A <hi>Jury</hi> of Gods own Impannel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, ſo that we may be ſure it was upright and impartial. <hi>Take twelve rods according to the number of the Tribes of Iſrael; And write the Prince of every Tribe his name upon his Rod. And lay them up in the Tabernacle of the Congregation before the Teſtimony, where I
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:66527:19"/> will meet with you. And it ſhall come to paſs</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 2. 3, 4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>that the mans Rod, whom I ſhall chuſe, ſhall bloſſome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Verdict,</hi> not given by way of <hi>Oracle;</hi> for they had no great confidence in <hi>Moſes,</hi> who was to report the Oracle. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God ſpeaks to their eyes by way of <hi>miracle;</hi> and ſo the <hi>Verdict</hi> is according to Gods own direction. <hi>And it came to paſs</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 8.</note> 
               <hi>on the morrow, That Moſes went into the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle of witneſs, and behold the Rod of Aaron for the houſe of Levi was budded, and brought forth buds, and bloomed bloſſoms, and yielded almonds.</hi> In the third the <hi>Record,</hi> we ſhall conſider, 1. the <hi>Exemplification</hi> of it; and 2. the <hi>Deſign.</hi> And theſe are expreſly in my Text, <hi>Refer virgam ut ſervetur in ſignum.</hi> And the Lord ſaid unto <hi>Moſes, Bring Aarons Rod again, before the Teſtimony, to be kept for a token againſt the Rebels.</hi> This I call the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplification</hi> of the Record, <hi>Et quieſcant que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relae;</hi> And <hi>thou ſhalt quite take away their murmurings from me, that they dye not.</hi> This is the <hi>Deſign, and purpoſe of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. We will begin with the <hi>Caſe, Aarons Caſe,</hi> and firſt of the <hi>Patron</hi> of it, which was <hi>Moſes: Dixit<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Dominus ad Moſem.</hi> The
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:66527:20"/> 
               <hi>Hierarchy</hi> of the Church was not of <hi>Moſes's</hi> Inſtitution. The God of <hi>Order</hi> eſtabliſhed an <hi>imparity</hi> amongſt the officers of the Church. <hi>Aaron and his Sons</hi> were advanced to the <hi>Prieſthood,</hi> and the <hi>Levites</hi> ſetled in a ſtate of <hi>Subordination</hi> to them, by Gods own appointment. <hi>Thou ſhalt appoint Aaron</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chap 6. 10.</note> 
               <hi>and his ſons, and they ſhall wait on their Prieſts office.</hi> They are immediately dedicated unto God to ſerve him in the higheſt ſphere of Miniſtration: <hi>And thou ſhalt give the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 9. Verſ. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Levites unto Aaron,</hi> and to what end? <hi>Bring the Tribe of Levi neer, and preſent them before Aaron the Prieſt, that they may Miniſter un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him.</hi> The Inveſtiture is from <hi>Moſes,</hi> but the Direction and Authority is from God himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes,</hi> we ſee, had good warrant for this; but the Peoples jealouſie ſuggeſted, that he had his own ends to ſerve under pretence of Gods Inſtitution. They ſuſpected he had a deſign to eſtabliſh his own Throne and an uſurped Prerogative; and they thought there was no way ſo likely to accompliſh this, as by advanceing his allies; his elder brother, <hi>Aaron,</hi> to the high-Prieſts Office. And if he could perſwade the People that
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:66527:20"/> this eſtabliſhment was by Gods own appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, while the Glory of the <hi>Myter</hi> did put out their eyes and dazle their judgments, he might take his Advantage to make himſelf an abſolute Prince over them. That this was their ſenſe is evident from their diſcourſe, <hi>Ye take too much upon you; will ye put out the eyes of this People? and wilt thou [Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes]</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 3, 13, 14.</note> 
               <hi>make thy ſelf altogether a Prince over us?</hi> Hereupon as well to vindicate the Integrity of <hi>Moſes,</hi> as the Authority of his own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, God appoints <hi>Moſes</hi> to be the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron</hi> of <hi>Aarons</hi> Caſe, <hi>Dixitque Dominus ad Moſen;</hi> And <hi>the Lord ſaid unto Moſes,</hi> &amp;c. 'Tis ſtrange an Office that lyes under ſo much contempt amongſt ſome, ſhould be a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſo much emulation amongſt the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Indeed it is a great Priviledg to have ſo free an acceſs to God, as the Prieſt ever had; and a great Dignity to be next <hi>Moſes</hi> (the Prince) as well in point of Honour as Authority. But if their eyes were dazled with the ſplendour of the <hi>Myter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 18. 1.</note> their heart ſhould have weighed what a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den it is <hi>to bear the iniquity of the Sanctuary, and of the Prieſthood.</hi> This haply might have taken off the envy, and we ſhould
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:66527:21"/> not have had ſo many <hi>Rivals</hi> to promote a Faction againſt the right <hi>Incumbent</hi> in the<note place="margin">vid. <hi>Bonfr.</hi> in Chap 16. 2.</note> holy Office. Ambition ſtarted the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, which was promoted by <hi>Corah</hi> out of envy, and the Sons of <hi>Ruben</hi> his confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates; and began upon this pretence. Before the<note place="margin">Num. 16. 1.</note> Tribe of <hi>Levi</hi> was ſeparated to the Prieſts Office, the firſt-born of every Tribe was hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, as it were by right of <hi>Primogeniture</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chap. 3. Verſ. 45.</note> to perform the duty. They took it ill to be diveſted of this Right (which the Law of nature had intailed upon them) and to ſee it tranſlated intirely upon <hi>Aaron</hi> and his Sons, created matter of envy and indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (eſpecially in <hi>Corah</hi> and the Sons of <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ben</hi>). If one Prieſt muſt needs be ſetled o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all the Tribes, why not the Son of <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ben,</hi> the firſt-born? For though his Father forfeited his birth-right, yet Gods Law doth<note place="margin">Gen. 49. 3. 1. Chron. 5. 1.</note> not extedn the penalty beyond the <hi>third</hi> or the <hi>fourth</hi> Generation; and by this time the intailed curſe being cut off, it is juſt his poſterity ſhould be reſtored to the right of Primogeniture. This was very plauſible for the <hi>Rubenites</hi> to plead, while they aimed likewiſe, in all probability, at the <hi>Scepter.</hi> But this would not ſerve <hi>Corah's</hi> turn, he
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:66527:21"/> affected an <hi>Eccleſiaſtical ſupremacy</hi> himſelf (ſo <hi>Moſes</hi> tells him:) But he could not tell<note place="margin">Chap 16. 10:</note> well how to make out his Title, for though he was of the Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> yet he was head but of the <hi>Second</hi> houſe; <hi>Aaron</hi> was of the <hi>firſt.</hi> He was therefore to gratifie<note place="margin">Exod 6. 21.</note> his envy by procuring <hi>Aarons</hi> Juriſdiction to be <hi>voted</hi> down, and his Power <hi>levelled,</hi> that himſelf might be exempted from all <hi>Canonical Obedience,</hi> and become an <hi>Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent.</hi> And then his Ambition ſuggeſted, That by his popularity and little Arts of inſinuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he might gather a numerous congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And to this end he courts the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,<note place="margin">Chap 16. 3.</note> and pleads the cauſe of a <hi>Godly party; Ye take too much upon you, ſeeing all the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation are holy, every one of them.</hi> And therefore ſufficiently qualified to <hi>chooſe</hi> their own Prieſt, or <hi>adminiſter</hi> to <hi>themſelves.</hi> This Doctrine did ſo bewitch the People, that (even after the <hi>Ringleaders</hi> of the Faction, <hi>Corah</hi> and the Sons of <hi>Ruben</hi> were removed by a Signal and Stupendous vengeance) <hi>all the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chap 16. 42.</note> 
               <hi>congregation</hi> (not one Tribe excepted) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired <hi>againſt Moſes and againſt Aaron,</hi> to carry on the deſign, until <hi>fourteen thouſand and ſeven hundred</hi> of them were ſwept away
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:66527:22"/> with a <hi>new</hi> plague, and the reſt ſilenced by a <hi>Miraculous</hi> deciſion of the controverſy. In the interim, how does <hi>Aaron</hi> the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant, behave himſelf in this quarrel? why, he ſhews himſelf (as becomes a <hi>Type</hi> of Chriſt) worthy that Office, which they maliciouſly contended to wreſt from him, when he ſees<note place="margin">Num. 16. 48.</note> that <hi>wrath is gon out and the plague begun:</hi> He takes his <hi>Cenſer</hi> to make an <hi>Atonement, and ſtanding between the dead and the living,</hi> He expoſeth his own life as a ſacrifice for theſe his enemies; but for his cauſe he pleads not one word, but ſubmits himſelf and it, wholly to him that judgeth righteouſly: and ſo we proceed to,</p>
            <p>2. The <hi>Trial.</hi> But had not a <hi>ſpecial Verdict</hi> paſt againſt them already? Had they not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged a <hi>judgment,</hi> upon the loſs of 15000 Souls, ſwept away by a threefold Vengeance, the <hi>devouring earth,</hi> the <hi>conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming fire,</hi> and a <hi>waſting plague?</hi> But this is thought imputable to ſome raſhneſs of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct in the buſineſs; or to <hi>Moſes's</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt and importunity with God. And ſo their Spirits being imbittered and their hearts hardened, thoſe judgments made no impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon them. In mercy therefore, God
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:66527:22"/> deals with them in cool blood, and ſummons them to a <hi>new Trial;</hi> wherein he vindicates the Authority of his own Inſtitution, and <hi>ſeals Aarons Pattent</hi> for the ſacred Office with a <hi>miracle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this <hi>Trial</hi> we are to conſider, 1. The <hi>Jury,</hi> 2. The <hi>Verdict.</hi> In the <hi>Jury</hi> we may conſider, 1. The <hi>nature,</hi> 2. The <hi>number,</hi> 3. The <hi>place</hi> of their meeting.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They are <hi>Rods.</hi> Men many times do ſo far degenerate, becom ſo unreaſonable, that God appeals to ſenſeleſs creatures to take up the diſpute and decide the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, that he has with them, <hi>Hear O ye mountains the Lords controverſie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, the <hi>Rod</hi> is an Emblem of <hi>Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> an Enſign of <hi>Juriſdiction. The Lord ſhall</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 110. Heb. 11. Pſal. 89. 32. Apoc. 21. 15.</note> 
               <hi>ſend the rod of thy power out of Sion.</hi> And there is a threefold uſe of the <hi>Rod,</hi> conſonant to that Emblematical. ſignification. For 1. <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port;</hi> for 2. <hi>Chaſtiſement;</hi> and 3. <hi>Menſuration.</hi> And it belongs to the juſtice of Authority to <hi>ſupport</hi> the weak and innocent, to chaſtiſe the wicked and impenitent, and to <hi>mete</hi> out re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and puniſhment reſpectively unto all. The <hi>Rods</hi> therefore are not unfitly put upon the <hi>Jury</hi> to find for the Prieſts office. And
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:66527:23"/> the <hi>Rods</hi> of <hi>Almond-Trees</hi> moſt oppoſite to this purpoſe; for this being the firſt of Trees that <hi>awakes</hi> out of the dead of Winter, and <hi>ſhoots</hi> up to <hi>cloath</hi> and <hi>dreſs</hi> it ſelf, to it belongs the right of <hi>Primogeniture</hi> amongſt the Trees; and therefore it is ſo much the fitter to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine upon what Tribe the <hi>Sacred Prieſthood,</hi> a ſpecial branch of the <hi>right</hi> of <hi>Primogeniture,</hi> is to be transferred.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For the <hi>number</hi> of theſe <hi>Rods,</hi> there is ſome difference amongſt Interpreters, becauſe the Tribe of <hi>Joſeph</hi> was divided into <hi>two</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, and had a <hi>double</hi> portion in the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and ſo upon that <hi>civil</hi> account, there were twelve Tribes beſides the Tribe of <hi>Levi;</hi> therefore ſome think there were twelve Rods beſides the Rod of <hi>Levi.</hi> But ſuch an inequality had been apt to breed another quarrel; and therefore it is more probable, there were but twelve Rods, according to the number of the Tribes in their Original; and that theſe Rods were all of the ſame ſtock, the ſame growth, the ſame gathering and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, that there might be no <hi>diſparity</hi> to beget new cavils touching the deciſion.</p>
            <p>And becauſe the Tribe of <hi>Levi</hi> was divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into two Families, though <hi>Corah</hi> head of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:66527:23"/> the <hi>ſecond</hi> Houſe, and <hi>Aaron</hi>'s Competitor or<note place="margin">Numb. 26. 11.</note> Adverſary at leaſt, was extinguiſhed, and his Sons (being preſerved by ſpecial Providence) probably had yielded the pre-eminence to <hi>Aaron,</hi> (deeming it ſufficient honour for them to be dignified with that luſtre that would be reflected upon them from the Glory of the head of their <hi>Elder</hi> Family,) yet to take off all colour of diſpute about the Succeſſion, God gave expreſs order, That <hi>Aaron</hi>'s, and not <hi>Levi</hi>'s name, ſhould be written upon the <hi>Rod</hi> for the <hi>Tribe</hi> of <hi>Levi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. For the <hi>place</hi> where this <hi>Jury</hi> of Rods were put together, it was the Tabernacle of<note place="margin">Verſ. 3.</note> the Covenant before the <hi>Teſtimony,</hi> before the <hi>Tables</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> by the <hi>Pot of Manna;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 94.</note> to ſignifie that the <hi>Rod</hi> is an excellent <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher of obedience to the Law;</hi> and if it prevails not to that effect, that then it is a ready in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument to drive us from the comfort of the <hi>Pot of Manna,</hi> the benefit of the <hi>Sacrament.</hi> Or it might be intended that the <hi>ſacredneſs</hi> of the place ſhould take away all ſuſpition of <hi>fraud,</hi> and add Authority to the <hi>miraculous obſignation</hi> of <hi>Aaron</hi>'s office. This being the <hi>place</hi> where God did vouchſafe to exhibit <hi>his Gracious preſence</hi> to determine them upon
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:66527:24"/> 
               <hi>appeal,</hi> in all <hi>doubtful</hi> Caſes: the <hi>Rods</hi> were placed here, to ſignifie, that this being a kind of <hi>Sacred Lottery,</hi> the event was wholly at Gods diſpoſal; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Greg. Nyſſ.</hi> That <hi>the grace of Prieſthood is not of men but of God. Ideo &amp;</hi> Aaron <hi>Sacerdotem ipſe elegit; ut non humana cupiditas in eligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do ſacerdote praeponderaret, ſed gratia Dei: non</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ep. l. 10. Ep. 82.</note> 
               <hi>voluntaria oblatio, nec propria aſſumptio, ſed caeleſtis vocatio,</hi> Ambroſ.</p>
            <p>And now this <hi>Emblematical Grand Jury.</hi> will afford us an excellent Definition of a <hi>Prieſt</hi> or <hi>Biſhop;</hi> he is a perſon ſlipt off the common ſtock of Mankind by a ſpecial act of ſeparation, not rooted in the earth, not fed with the <hi>crude</hi> juices of nature, to ſoften and infeeble him, to make him pliant to the <hi>bent</hi> of evil inclinations; but mortified to the motions of the fleſh; dead to the Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the World; that being impregnated with bleſſings ſupernatural, with grace and knowledg, he may bring forth abundant fruit for the ſervice of Gods Church. And the <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict</hi> which went for <hi>Aaron</hi> repreſents him to be ſuch a perſon: For <hi>behold, his Rod had budded buds, and brought forth leaves, and bloomed bloſſoms, and yielded Almonds.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 8.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:66527:24"/>
            <p>Here is a <hi>production,</hi> which nature never had a due conception of, at leaſt never travel'd for it. A <hi>dry Rod</hi> ſwell'd into <hi>turgent buds,</hi> and buds dilated into lovely <hi>bloſſoms,</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted into wholſome <hi>fruits,</hi> and all <hi>ex tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore;</hi> a <hi>threefold</hi> miracle to render <hi>Aaron</hi>'s election the more certain and unqueſtionable. <hi>Buds</hi> and <hi>Flowers</hi> and <hi>Fruit;</hi> here's proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for <hi>poſterity</hi> by an orderly <hi>ſucceſſion.</hi> And the order of their pullulation is an evidence that Gods Grace does not deſtroy <hi>Nature,</hi> or pervert the <hi>common courſe</hi> of it; but only <hi>aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, quicken,</hi> and <hi>advance</hi> her in her operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Auſtin</hi> calls this Rod, <hi>Sacramentum Sacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotale;</hi>
               <note place="margin">De Temp. Ser. 99. ep. l. 1. ep. 50. Lib. 10. ep. 82. Origen. Pelu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiot. Ambr. Auſtin. <hi>Fructus nucis amaram qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem &amp; aſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram cortium habet, ſub qua latet quod eſt eſculentum, &amp;c.</hi> Theod. &amp; Hier. in Jer. 1.</note> and <hi>Iſ. Peluſiot, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, The Type of the Prieſthood.</hi> And what doth it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie, <hi>Niſi quod nunquam Sacerdotalis marceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat gratia,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Ambroſe.</hi> The Fathers ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve further of this Tree, that the <hi>outſide,</hi> the <hi>rinde,</hi> the <hi>husk,</hi> the <hi>ſhell,</hi> are <hi>hard</hi> and <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtringent, ſharp</hi> and <hi>bitter;</hi> but the <hi>inſide,</hi> the <hi>fruit,</hi> the <hi>kernel,</hi> are <hi>ſweet, nutritive,</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing.</hi> This is a ſignificant <hi>Hyerogliphick</hi> of the Prieſts duty. It inſtructs him to be <hi>vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant</hi> and <hi>active</hi> in his office, <hi>auſtere</hi> and <hi>morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied</hi> in his life, <hi>patient</hi> and <hi>hardy</hi> to endure
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:66527:25"/> the ſtorms of reproach and oppoſition, while he is <hi>diſcharging</hi> himſelf in a <hi>ſalutary fruitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> Let him be <hi>cloathed</hi> with the <hi>leaves</hi> and <hi>bloſſoms</hi> of a decent Converſation; but laden with the <hi>fruits</hi> of all good works; that the Church under the inſpection of ſuch Paſtors may be as a <hi>Garden of Nuts,</hi> and the <hi>Spouſe</hi> delight to deſcend into it with his train of Graces, and inconceivable conſolation.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, all Prieſts have their Rods; but all Rods are not thus <hi>florid,</hi> thus <hi>fruitful.</hi> Such as are ſo, without all peradventure are of Gods election and eſtabliſhment, as was <hi>Aaron.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now I hope ſuch as are of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> of what Tribe ſoever, will ſubmit to Gods <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitration,</hi> and be reconciled to <hi>Aaron,</hi> and <hi>kiſs</hi> his Rod; pay a due regard, a dutiful veneration to that Office and Miniſtry, which God hath vouchſafed to dignify with a threefold miracle. To this end a publick <hi>Record</hi> is made of it, to be kept inviolable. <hi>And the Lord ſaid unto Moſes, bring Aarons Rod again before the teſtimony,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>Before the teſtimony,</hi> That whenſoever they came to <hi>conſult</hi> God about any <hi>emer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent</hi> difficulty, they might not preſume to ſeek his aſſiſtance to <hi>degrade</hi> the Prieſthood,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:66527:25"/> or <hi>cut</hi> off the line of ſucceſſion, which he had <hi>eſtabliſhed</hi> by ſuch wonderful <hi>Prodigies,</hi> and to which he had aſſigned <hi>Sanctuary</hi> in his <hi>holy place;</hi> for thither the Rod is brought, and brought thither it is.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t ſervetur,</hi> that it might be kept; ſuch as attempt to undermine Gods ſacred Conſtitutions by the rudeneſs of popular tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults, do but make them take the firmer roots, and ingage God the more to ſhew <hi>ſigns</hi> and <hi>wonders</hi> for their preſervation. <hi>Aarons</hi> Rod ſhall find <hi>Sanctuary,</hi> and be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved <hi>in perpetuam rei memoriam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t ſervetur in ſignum,</hi> It ſhall be kept <hi>for a ſign.</hi> Mans memory is naturally trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous; and nothing can ſpoil it ſooner than ingratitude and envy. Therefore God does here teach us <hi>an Art of Memory,</hi> by preſcribing <hi>tokens</hi> to cure us of our forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs; ſuch <hi>memorials</hi> being <hi>ſignificant</hi> to<note place="margin">Hic et Chap. 16. 38.</note> the uſe of <hi>edifying:</hi> though but <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> God preſcribes them, and though they be<note place="margin">Joſ. 22. 10.</note> but of <hi>Mans</hi> Inſtitution, he allows of them. Such <hi>ſigns</hi> do not <hi>confer</hi> Grace <hi>ex opere operato,</hi> not by any <hi>real efficacy;</hi> no nor yet by way of <hi>impetration,</hi> they cannot do it. They have no <hi>Natural Power,</hi> no <hi>divine
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:66527:26"/> Promiſe</hi> for it. But they are fair <hi>Objects</hi> to excite and refreſh the Memory. And he that will either <hi>eſchew evil or do good,</hi> muſt firſt remember that it is his duty, and in this ſence and to this effect, every <hi>monument</hi> of Gods Juſtice, every remanent <hi>inſtance</hi> of the Divine Mercy, may become <hi>ſacramental</hi> to us.</p>
            <p>But had Almighty God left himſelf and his Servant <hi>Aaron without witneſs</hi> hitherto? No, thoſe 250 men with <hi>Corah</hi> and ſome<note place="margin">Numb. 26. 10.</note> others, they became <hi>a ſign.</hi> And the <hi>braſen Cenſers</hi> of thoſe that offer'd incenſe, were made a <hi>ſign</hi> too; they were converted into <hi>plates</hi> for a <hi>covering</hi> of the Altar to be a<note place="margin">Chap. 16. 40.</note> 
               <hi>Memorial</hi> unto the children of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> They could not approach the Altar, but the <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection</hi> of thoſe <hi>plates</hi> was a cleer conviction of their late Miſcarriages. But when men will proceed in their ſin after judgment, they provoke God to erect more <hi>ſigns</hi> to upbraid their ſtubbornneſs and ingratitude; when they importune him contrary to his expreſs Revelations, they get nothing by it in the end, but the <hi>brand</hi> of a more <hi>laſting</hi> infamy: For</p>
            <p>4. This Rod is kept <hi>in ſignum Rebellium
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:66527:26"/> filiorum Iſrael,</hi> for a token againſt the <hi>Rebels.</hi> God had paſt an <hi>Act of oblivion</hi> upon <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi>'s Interceſſion, in favour of this People,<note place="margin">Numb. 14. 21.</note> 
               <hi>Dimiſi peccatum populi hujus, juxta verbum tuum.</hi> But God forgets our ſins, <hi>upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition</hi> we keep a <hi>Record</hi> and <hi>repent</hi> of them. If we do <hi>repeat them,</hi> we <hi>revive</hi> the memory of our <hi>paſt</hi> tranſgreſſions; and ſet up a light, by which thoſe dim characters of our guilt, over which the hand of charity had drawn a <hi>curtain,</hi> become legible. And yet even here the ineſtimable Goodneſs of God is remarkable; he does ſo mercifully chaſtize their pride, that the teſtimony of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumacy ſhall be the means of their cure, a proviſion for their amendment, and an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidote againſt the peril of <hi>Recidivation.</hi> This Rod is to be kept for a token, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t quieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant querelae, ne moriantur.</hi> To take away their Murmurings from me, (<hi>yea and againſt me</hi> too, for they were not ſo much againſt <hi>Aaron</hi> as <hi>againſt the Lord</hi>); That they die not, and that was the Deſign in this Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t quieſcant querelae,</hi> to ſilence and ſtill their <hi>Murmurings.</hi> Ambition is reſtleſs and knows no bounds. <hi>Cogitet qui honorem
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:66527:27"/> affectat tempeſtatem ſe affectare.</hi> He that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecteth Honour does court a tempeſt, for, <hi>Quid eſt poteſtas culminis niſi tempeſtas mentis?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Philo.</note> Such as climb the <hi>pinnacle</hi> of Ambition are<note place="margin">pſal. 106. 16.</note> toſſed with the greateſt <hi>tempeſts.</hi> Theſe <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites</hi> began with <hi>Envy,</hi> proceeded to <hi>Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring,</hi> and at laſt grew inſolent even to an <hi>inſurrection;</hi> they make a forcible <hi>entry</hi> upon the ſacred office, and commit a noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>riot,</hi> wherein many thouſands periſh. God having <hi>inſtalled Aaron</hi> and his Sons in the Prieſts Office, added this <hi>ſanction</hi> to the<note place="margin">Numb. 3. 10.</note> eſtabliſhment, <hi>The ſtranger that cometh near ſhall be put to death.</hi> Yet their Ambition was grown ſo great, and their Animoſities ſo high; That God ſaw it time to take up the quarrel, elſe all the Tribes had died in it. The earth <hi>ſwallowed</hi> them up; and yet they <hi>murmured:</hi> The <hi>Fire</hi> conſumed them; and yet they <hi>murmured;</hi> The <hi>Plague</hi> made havock of them, and yet they <hi>murmured.</hi> And this ſpirit of <hi>perverſneſs</hi> was ſo great a provocation to a noble and ingenuous nature, God could not but be <hi>ſevere</hi> in puniſhing<note place="margin">Numb. 14. 10.</note> of it. They had rejected their <hi>Guides,</hi> and were ready to ſtone any charitable <hi>Informer.</hi> Nothing but a laſting <hi>miracle</hi> can <hi>ſhame</hi> and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:66527:27"/> 
               <hi>ſilence</hi> them; <hi>Aarons</hi> Rod <hi>inſhrin'd</hi> in the <hi>ſanctuary,</hi> muſt compoſe their ſpirits, and make peace betwixt God and them, betwixt them and themſelves. If it cannot <hi>heal</hi> their perverſities, it will ſo far charm them into temper, as to <hi>bridle</hi> and <hi>reſtrain</hi> their bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. They will now ſuffer <hi>Aaron quietly</hi> to perform his Office; and his <hi>Miniſtry</hi> will be a means to keep off future judgments. And to this end, the Lord ſaid unto <hi>Moſes, Bring Aarons Rod again, before the teſtimony to be kept,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>What <hi>Aaron</hi> was amongſt the <hi>Tribes</hi> of<note place="margin">Application.</note> 
               <hi>Ifrael,</hi> the ſame, upon the matter, is the <hi>Biſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>op</hi> in his <hi>Province,</hi> and <hi>Corah</hi> was the <hi>figure</hi> of ſuch as make <hi>Rents</hi> and <hi>Schiſmes</hi> in the Church of Chriſt; who are therefore ſaid to have periſhed <hi>in the gainſaying of Corah,</hi> as<note place="margin">Jud. Ep. v. 11.</note> in their <hi>Repreſentative.</hi> And yet, Good God! What an <hi>Inſurrection</hi> hath been made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us upon that account? <hi>Aaron,</hi> he was <hi>voted</hi> down and <hi>depoſed;</hi> and in fine you cannot forget what became of <hi>Moſes.</hi> But (to make haſte out of that wilderneſs, and from amongſt thoſe <hi>fiery ſerpents</hi> that ſtung ſo deadly) <hi>Moſes</hi> muſt be recalled to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe our <hi>tumults,</hi> to ſtill our <hi>murmurings</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:66527:28"/> and ſettle us in Tranquillity. To this end <hi>Dixit Dominus,</hi> The Lord ſpake unto his Majeſty; not <hi>Immediately</hi> by a voice from Heaven, but by the voice of holy Scriptures and ancient Councils; by the voice of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Experience, by the voice of fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Laws and Cuſtoms; by the voice of Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Fathers and dutiful Sons; by the voice of <hi>Royal blood,</hi> and by the voice of our great diſorders and confuſions. Many <hi>Cobwebs</hi> were to be ſwept down from our Church-win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, and much rubbiſh to be ſwept out of our Church-doors; and much duſt to be bruſht off the garments of <hi>inferiour</hi> Prieſts and Levites; ſome things were amiſs in the houſe of God, and no ſuch <hi>Rule</hi> as <hi>Aarons</hi> Rod to <hi>ſquare</hi> out a <hi>Reformation.</hi> Theſe were the Lords <hi>voice</hi> crying unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> to the King, <hi>refer virgam,</hi> bring the Rod again, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But had we not a <hi>Rod</hi> already? <hi>A rod</hi> with a <hi>vengeance,</hi> a Rod of <hi>Corah's</hi> own ſtock, of <hi>Corah's</hi> own <hi>gathering; Floruit virga,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 7. 10, 11.</note> 
               <hi>germinavit ſuperbia, iniquitas ſurrexit in virga.</hi> Ours was juſt of the ſame conſtitution. The <hi>Radix,</hi> the root of it was <hi>iniquity,</hi> and that branched out into oppreſſion and violence:
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:66527:28"/> A rod of <hi>Iron</hi> this was, that broke the <hi>Royal Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and beat down the <hi>Royal Branches,</hi> and <hi>daſht</hi> the Church in pieces; <hi>A ragged ſtaffe,</hi> whoſe <hi>fangs</hi> were <hi>ſteel'd</hi> with Malice, and <hi>died</hi> with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent blood. It knockt down <hi>Moſes,</hi> and thruſt out <hi>Aaron:</hi> away with ſuch a Rod, and God be thanked, this Rod of the wicked did <hi>not reſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the lot of the Righteous;</hi> though it was ſomewhat long in motion, <hi>rowling up and down,</hi> yet it did not, it could not <hi>reſt,</hi> it was acted by ſuch a <hi>vertiginous ſpirit.</hi> This <hi>Rod</hi> was at laſt thrown away, and <hi>Moſes</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored. <hi>And the Lord ſaid unto Moſes, bring Aarons Rod again before the teſtimony.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not a Rod of <hi>Aarons</hi> own <hi>growth</hi> or <hi>ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering,</hi> but <hi>a plant which the Heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath planted:</hi> For <hi>no man taketh this</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Honour to himſelf, but he that is called of God as was Aaron.</hi> Our Rod is that, which undoubtedly ſprung from the <hi>root</hi> of <hi>Jeſſe: As</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 20.</note> 
               <hi>my Father ſent me, ſo I ſend you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Out of that ground it <hi>ſhooteth</hi> up in the Church of God; and all <hi>Antiquity</hi> ſets forth the <hi>Lineage</hi> of it, in the <hi>viſible ſucceſſion</hi> of Biſhops, from the Apoſtles, in the ſeveral Churches of their plantation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Tabernaculum,</hi> Bring it into the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle;
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:66527:29"/> there it hath the Approbation of Gods eye, the protection of his <hi>Preſence.</hi> From hence therefore it muſt take direction to miniſter in ſubordination to the Authority and Honour thereof; there it is inſtalled, <hi>ut ſervetur in ſignum;</hi> lodged there in ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; obliged therefore to ſerve the <hi>Intereſt</hi> of the Church, which is the Intereſt of God and of immortal Souls. In order hereunto it is ſet up <hi>in ſignum,</hi> for a ſign; Yes, and <hi>in ſignum ad ſagittam</hi> too, as a mark for the Arrow. It is the Prophets complaint, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold I and the children, which God hath given me, are for ſigns and wonders.</hi> It was our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours own lot, he was ſet up, <hi>in ſignum contradictionis,</hi> a ſign liable to great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction; againſt him they ſhot out their <hi>Arrows,</hi> even <hi>bitter words.</hi> And, if ſo bold with <hi>Aaron</hi> himſelf, they will not forbear his <hi>ſubſtitute;</hi> if they forbear not the <hi>chief Biſhop,</hi> they will not ſpare his <hi>ſhadow.</hi> As long as <hi>Aaron</hi> is ſet up <hi>for a ſign</hi> in the Church, there will be found ſuch <hi>Archers;</hi> we have them in our Text, with their quiver full of bitter Arrows; nay their Arrows are <hi>upon the ſtring, and upon the flight</hi> too. As long as they continue to be, <hi>filii Rebellionis,</hi> while
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:66527:29"/> they retain their froward diſpoſition, <hi>non qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſcunt querelae,</hi> we ſhall never be free from <hi>Murmurings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But are there any of this <hi>breed</hi> left in our <hi>Iſrael?</hi> Has not the Gracious <hi>Act of oblivion</hi> quite extinguiſhed this unquiet ſpirit? <note place="margin">1 Sam. 15. 14.</note> If it has, what meaneth then this <hi>lowing</hi> and this <hi>bleating,</hi> which we hear? Are there not a many <hi>Murmurers</hi> attempting to exaſperate the people into a new inſurrection, that they may once more wreſt the Rod out of the hand of <hi>Aaron?</hi> And do theſe men look for a <hi>ſign</hi> too? yes, they do, and they might ſee <hi>a wonderful ſign from heaven,</hi> if they were not blinded with pride and prejudice, and an obſtinate Spirit: <hi>Ecce Dominus,</hi> behold the Lord himſelf hath given us a ſign; <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſti</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 69. 6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>metuentibus,</hi> thou haſt given <hi>a token for them that fear thee.</hi> At the tears and prayers of the Church, God ſaved her with the whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome defence of his own right-hand. For the change amongſt us, by the Reſtauration of the King, was no other than <hi>mutatio dextrae Altiſſimi,</hi> wrought by the right-hand of the moſt-high. <hi>A ſign</hi> from heaven this was, without all <hi>peradventure.</hi> Yet theſe men are not ſatisfied, they look for, and preach for,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:66527:30"/> and pray for, <hi>another ſign,</hi> and what ſign would they have? The <hi>ſeven Angels</hi> with the <hi>ſeven</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 15.</note> 
               <hi>plagues</hi> and <hi>vials</hi> of Gods wrath? Would they have more fire come down from heaven? Alas! <hi>They know not what ſpirit they are of</hi> He that came not to deſtroy mens Souls, but to ſave them; did not ordain <hi>Aarons</hi> Rod for ſuch a ſign. If that Rod did turn<note place="margin">Num. 20. 9.</note> the <hi>rock into water</hi> (as ſome have imagined) yet, to be ſure, it did not turn <hi>the water into blood:</hi> It may bring forth <hi>contrition</hi> and <hi>refreſhment,</hi> but not <hi>deſtruction:</hi> It <hi>bodes</hi> bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: things to mankind, even to theſe <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractory</hi> and ſtubborn children: 'Tis <hi>ſignum ſalutare ne moriantur;</hi> A ſoveraign preſervative, <hi>That they die not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That is the end for which the Rod is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced and <hi>depoſited</hi> in the ſanctuary. This<note place="margin">2 Cor. 10. 8.</note> Power of Diſcipline, <hi>Dedit nobis in aedifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cationem,</hi> God hath given it for edification, ſaith the Apoſtle, and not for your deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And yet he hath taught us to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh betwixt <hi>yours</hi> and <hi>you.</hi> Something<note place="margin">2 Cor. 10. 8.</note> was to be deſtroyed in them, though not their Perſons; yet their <hi>Carnalities,</hi> their <hi>vices,</hi> their <hi>Schiſmes</hi> and <hi>Diſorders,</hi> Theſe works of the fleſh. The Rod is to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:66527:30"/> 
               <hi>in interitum carnis,</hi> for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the fleſh, <hi>That the ſpirit may be</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 5. 5.</note> 
               <hi>ſaved in the day of the Lord Jeſus.</hi> Morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication is the way to life, and Reformation<note place="margin">Jam. 5. ult.</note> the door of ſafety, <hi>He that converteth a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner from the errour of his way, ſhall ſave a Soul from death.</hi> This is the right Method; Gods Method in the Text, <hi>et quieſcant que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relae,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Thou ſhalt quite take away their Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murings,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>We ſee then why the Rod is placed in the ſanctuary; not ſo much for <hi>Aaron's</hi> own advantage, that he may pride himſelf in the Power and Beauty of it, but for the <hi>benefit</hi> of others, even of ſuch as do moſt oppoſe it. The remoter end is, <hi>ne moriantur,</hi> that they die not; but in order to this, the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate end is, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t quieſcant querelae eorum,</hi> to ſtill <hi>their murmurings:</hi> The oure muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin here, care muſt be taken in the firſt place, as much as is poſſible <hi>to take away their complaints and murmurings,</hi> and how ſhall that be effected?</p>
            <p>Why, <hi>Virga eſt mater diſciplinae,</hi> the Rod will open the eyes, if it be adminiſtred with<note place="margin">1 Sam. 14. 27.</note> a little <hi>honey</hi> applied to the top of it; when the <hi>aſperity</hi> is ſweetned with <hi>mildneſs</hi> and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:66527:31"/> compaſſion, <hi>The Rod and reproof giveth wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 29. 14.</note> If the <hi>viper</hi> be beaten with a rod, it takes away his venom, and he becomes an excellent <hi>Antidote</hi> againſt poiſon. If we cannot <hi>heal</hi> their perverſities, at leaſt we may ſtill their <hi>murmurings.</hi> And to this end the conſtitution of the Rod is very conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.</p>
            <p>It muſt be a <hi>ſtreight</hi> Rod, that the infliction<note place="margin">Deut. 25. 2.</note> may be equal to the fault, <hi>eſt enim verus prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſul virga recta, aequaliter juſtitiam exercens at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſemper vigilans.</hi> It muſt be a <hi>ſolid</hi> Rod<note place="margin">H. P. ad. Ez. 3.</note> to ſupport the weak, and a <hi>ſmart</hi> Rod to correct the wicked, and a <hi>ſtiff</hi> Rod to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the Innocent. Or (to keep ſtill to the <hi>Metaphor</hi>) it ſhould have theſe properties; It ſhould be, 1. <hi>ſolid, 2. vital, 3. florid,</hi> and 4. <hi>fruitful.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. A <hi>ſolid</hi> Rod, not <hi>hollow, looſe</hi> or <hi>ſpun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezok. 19. 11. Chap. 2. 4. 6. Chap. 3. 8, 9.</note> like a <hi>cane:</hi> For it is concern'd many times to encounter with a <hi>Rock;</hi> the heart of <hi>flint,</hi> and the face of <hi>braſs;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it had need be <hi>ſolid</hi> and <hi>ſteel'd</hi> with Reſolution, that it may not yield to the <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications,</hi> nor receive the <hi>impreſſions</hi> of an importune and ſtubborn ſpirit.</p>
            <p>2. It muſt be a <hi>vital</hi> Rod, (and they ſay
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:66527:31"/> 
               <hi>Aaron's</hi> Rod did never <hi>wither,</hi> was never barren after it was depoſited in the <hi>ſanctuary.</hi>) And this life muſt appear in a <hi>threefold ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination;</hi> it muſt bud, 1. a <hi>vital eye,</hi> 2. a <hi>vital tongue,</hi> 3. a <hi>vital ſting.</hi> 1. A <hi>vital eye,</hi> and ſo it muſt be, <hi>virga vigilans,</hi> like that of<note place="margin">Jer. 1. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Jeremy,</hi> A <hi>watching Rod.</hi> 2. A <hi>vital tongue,</hi> and ſo it muſt be, <hi>virga clamitans,</hi> like that<note place="margin">Mic. 6. 9.</note> of <hi>Micah,</hi> a <hi>preaching Rod.</hi> 3. A <hi>vital ſting,</hi> and ſo it muſt be, <hi>virga ſtimulans,</hi> like that of St. <hi>Paul, a goading and a quickning</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4. ult.</note> 
               <hi>Rod.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. It muſt be a <hi>watching</hi> Rod, <hi>Vigilat autem virga, cuncta populi peccata conſiderans, ut percutiat et corripiat delinquentes.</hi> I have<note place="margin">Hieron. in Jer. 1. 11. Ezek. 33. 8. Heb. 13. 17. and 2 Tim. 4. 5.</note> made thee a <hi>watchman,</hi> ſaith the Lord to the Prophet, The very eſſence of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops Office conſiſteth in a <hi>ſuperintendency,</hi> his work is <hi>to watch for Souls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. A <hi>preaching Rod,</hi> if it be a genuine Rod of <hi>Aaron,</hi> it will ſpeak to every man, and to every ſin in its own Language. And St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> tells us, that two things are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite for corection and reproof, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>a diſcreet mildneſs</hi> with <hi>an ingenious liberty of ſpeech. Plus tamen erga corrigendos agat benevolentia quam ſeveritas; plus cohor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:66527:32"/> quam commotio, plus charitas quam poteſtas,</hi> ſaith <hi>Leo.</hi> Kindneſs is more prevalent to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the correction of Delinquents, than ſeverity; charity of more efficacy than an imperious Power. For ſome diſpoſitions (as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> obſerves) are wrought upon, <hi>magis docendo quam jubendo, magis monendo quam minando;</hi> more by <hi>Perſwaſion</hi> than by<note place="margin">1 Cor. 4. 21.</note> 
               <hi>menaces;</hi> ſuch diſpoſitions as are unrelen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at <hi>the ſpirit of meekneſs,</hi> to ſuch other ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications are highly neceſſary; and upon this account, the Rod is</p>
            <p>3. <hi>Virga ſtimulans,</hi> a ſmart and goading Rod; and in this caſe, the great Apoſtle, out of very charity, reſolves to uſe ſharpneſs.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 13. 2, 10.</note> The virtue of good-men is not <hi>ſine cuſpide vel aculeo,</hi> not without ſome ſting; and there are ſome tempers will require it.</p>
            <p>Yet I would not have this Rod turned into<note place="margin">Exod. 7. 12. 2 Tim. 3. 8.</note> a Serpent, unleſs it be with a deſign to ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low up the Rods of <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres,</hi> when they bewitch the People to withſtand <hi>Moſes.</hi> If any be ſo obſtinate that they will not be corrected by <hi>Aaron's</hi> Rod; neither o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient to the voice, nor awed by the eye, nor quickned by the ſting of it; eſpecially if any be ſo inſolent as to wreſt the Rod out of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:66527:32"/> 
               <hi>Aaron</hi>'s hand; if he provokes <hi>Aaron</hi> to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Rod be thrown out after him, and that becomes a Serpent to him, he may thank his own ſtubbornneſs for that Tranſubſtantiation; for inſtead of a gentle Rod he deſerves to be whipt with Scorpions. The Prophet <hi>Jeremy</hi> ſaw a <hi>Rod,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 1. 12, 13.</note> 
               <hi>and a ſeething Pot</hi> too; and it is the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Origen, Si ergo tali virga</hi> (Diſciplinae) <hi>non emendaris, in cacabum mitteris, &amp; caca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus</hi>
               <note place="margin">in Pſal. 38. Homil. 2.</note> 
               <hi>ſuccendetur.</hi> If the Rod of Diſcipline cannot reform thee, thou ſhalt be caſt into the ſeething Pot to be conſumed.</p>
            <p>3. It muſt be a <hi>florid Rod;</hi> ſome leaves it ſhould have, not broad enough to lodg or ſhelter Serpents, but ſoveraign to heal, and then to hide the ſcar and blemiſh of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm and ſurprized Patient. But ſome ſores are ſo deep, foul, and offenſive, they muſt be drawn and laid open, in order to their cure; to furniſh leaves to cover ſuch, is to skin o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver an old ſore, till it rankles, till it become more noiſome and contagious.</p>
            <p>But to make the Rod <hi>florid</hi> it muſt have <hi>bloſſoms</hi> as well as <hi>leaves.</hi> It is expected (what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Habits are in faſhion amongſt others) that the Prieſts ſhould be <hi>cloathed</hi> with <hi>righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs</hi>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:66527:33"/> and <hi>ſalvation;</hi> that they ſhould be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued<note place="margin">Pſal. 132. 16:</note> with the flower of Learning, and the beauty of Holineſs. And why ſhould not this have the advantage of Wealth and Honour to adorn and dreſs it up, as well as other Rods? Though ſuch Secular acceſſions can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not make it the more Sacred, yet they may make it the more awful, which will make it alſo the more ſerviceable, both to the Church of God, and to <hi>Moſes</hi> his Vicegerent. And this would be a means to make it what it ſhould be.</p>
            <p>4. A <hi>fruitful</hi> Rod; ſome perhaps do real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mind nothing, but the leaves and bloſſoms to cloth and adorn them. So they may be kept warm and gay, they care for nothing elſe. But as <hi>Leo</hi> hath it, <hi>Tua Conſcientia ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norem</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ep. 93. Chap. 16.</note> 
               <hi>ſibi debitum vindicant, qui pro anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſibi creditis non laborant? Beſtiae irruunt, &amp; ſepta ovium non claudunt. Fures inſidian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp; excubias non praetendunt. Morbi cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breſcunt, &amp; remedia nulla proſpiciunt. Feed</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mic. 7. 14.</note> 
               <hi>thy flock with thy Rod,</hi> ſaith the Lord to his Prophet. The flock muſt be fed, and to that effect the Rod muſt be fruitful.</p>
            <p>There are bitter Almonds whoſe virtue is to allay the fumes, digeſt the crudities and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:66527:33"/> dry up the inundations of Intemperance, to open Obſtructions, thoſe of Covetouſneſs and Oppreſſion, to expel the wind, that <hi>flatus</hi> of pride and vanity, to purge the <hi>reins</hi> and the <hi>inner</hi> man of all inordinate luſts and paſſons, and very uſeful to ſmooth the skin of a Chriſtians <hi>outward converſation,</hi> to make it beautiful and lovely. And there are ſweet Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds too, which afford an oyl and milk to cloſe the wounds of a broken heart, to refreſh the weak, to cool the <hi>Calentures</hi> of diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered Conſciences, and bring them to repoſe and comfort.</p>
            <p>When we have ſuch <hi>ſolid</hi> and ſuch <hi>vital,</hi> ſuch <hi>florid</hi> and ſuch <hi>fruitful</hi> Rods as theſe ſet before the flock. Methinks we ſhould all be of <hi>Jacobs</hi> breed, our inward concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and outward productions; our hearts and our works ſhould be of the <hi>ſame</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion, by the <hi>transforming</hi> Power of a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py imitation.</p>
            <p>To conclude, life conſiſteth in <hi>motion,</hi> and the <hi>vigour</hi> of life diſcovers it ſelf in the <hi>quickneſs</hi> of that motion; and even by the conſtitution of his Rod, <hi>Aaron</hi> is inſtructed
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:66527:34"/> to uſe <hi>Expedition</hi> in the Adminiſtration of his <hi>Diſcipline.</hi> For the <hi>Almond-tree</hi> hath its name from the <hi>forwardneſs</hi> of it's pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions. When cauſes, which fall under the <hi>Inſpection</hi> of this <hi>Rod,</hi> are kept too long before they come to a <hi>Deciſion,</hi> this is an <hi>ill ſign;</hi> and provokes juſtly to <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint</hi> and <hi>murmuring.</hi> It argues the Rod to be <hi>blind</hi> or <hi>dumb; ſoft</hi> or <hi>ſtupid;</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>ſting</hi> or <hi>life,</hi> not like the Rod that <hi>ſhoots</hi> up by Gods appointment; for that<note place="margin">Jer. 1. 11, 12.</note> is followed with <hi>a ſpeedy ſentence, and a due execution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let the Rod be <hi>Expeditious</hi> in its <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs,</hi> that there be no cauſe of <hi>murmuring</hi> upon that account, and then men will ſtand in <hi>awe</hi> of the <hi>ſting,</hi> and <hi>reverence</hi> the <hi>eye</hi> and <hi>obey</hi> the <hi>voice</hi> of it. And not only ſo, but finding <hi>ſhelter</hi> and <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection</hi> in the <hi>leaves,</hi> Beauty and Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the <hi>bloſſoms,</hi> Food, Phyſick and refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the <hi>fruit,</hi> they will delight to dwell under the ſhadow of it. When they ſee it Soveraign to <hi>heal</hi> and <hi>ſweeten</hi> all our bitter waters of ſtrife, they will really believe of this, what the <hi>Jews</hi> do but
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:66527:34"/> fable of that other, That it deſcends from the <hi>tree of life;</hi> They will cry out <hi>Servetur</hi> endeavour to have it <hi>flouriſh,</hi> and pray that it may be <hi>preſerved</hi> and <hi>proſper,</hi> in the Church amongſt us, to the Worlds end, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
